<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithful history of the northern affairs of Ireland from the late K. James accession to the crown, to the siege of Londonderry : giving a true account of the occasions of the miscarriages there, and of the reasons why the gentry abandon'd those parts / by a person who bore a great share in those transactions.</title>
            <author>Person who bore a great share in those transactions.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40770</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16682</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12037683</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12037683</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52913</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40770)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52913)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 67:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithful history of the northern affairs of Ireland from the late K. James accession to the crown, to the siege of Londonderry : giving a true account of the occasions of the miscarriages there, and of the reasons why the gentry abandon'd those parts / by a person who bore a great share in those transactions.</title>
                  <author>Person who bore a great share in those transactions.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randall Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1688-1689.</term>
               <term>Londonderry (Northern Ireland) --  History --  Siege, 1688-1689.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52913:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52913:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FAITHFUL HISTORY OF THE NORTHERN AFFAIRS OF IRELAND: FROM The Late K. <hi>JAMES</hi> Acceſſion to the Crown, TO THE Siege of <hi>LONDONDERRY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Giving a True Account of the Occaſions of the Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages there: And of the Reaſons why the Gentry abandon'd thoſe Parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Perſon who bore a great Share in thoſe Tranſactions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license_to_print">
                        <p>LICENS'D</p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Decemb.</hi> 10. 1689.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Randall Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers Hall.</hi> M DC XC.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:52913:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52913:2"/>
            <head>A FAITHFUL HISTORY OF THE <hi>NORTHERN</hi> Affairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>NO ſooner was the late King <hi>Jumes</hi> advanced to the Throne, but he fixed his whole ſtudy upon the Eſtabliſhment of his darling Twins, <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery;</hi> and having by ſeveral Inſtances formerly experienced the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Averſion to the Principles of that Religion, he therefore firſt ſet himſelf to conſider ſuch Methods as might beſt ſerve for the Introduction of it, without giving them too near a Proſpect of the Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on intended. It was ſor this reaſon thought fit that <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould be the firſt unhappy Scene of the enſuing Tragedy, where ſuch a Change ſeemed very practicable; for the far greater number of Inhabitants being naturally Slaves to the Yoke of <hi>Rome,</hi> could not but welcome the Chains of a Popiſh Tyrant; yet was not this to be effected on a ſudden for fear of alarming <hi>England,</hi> which was not at that time brought under the Awe of a Standing Army; beſides, the moſt conſiderable part of the Forces then in <hi>Ireland,</hi> conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch as were Proteſtants, obliged the King to a more wary Proſecution of his Deſigns. It was therefore conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to move by ſlower ſteps, and to continue the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Affairs in ſuch hands, as ſhould ſeem to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, that his Popiſh Councils might carry the better Gloſs, and his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects be leſs ſenſible of his varniſht Deſigns. Thus <hi>Ireland</hi> languiſh'd under the unhappy Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of being ruined by its pretended Friends, when in <hi>England</hi> the unwary Compliance of ſuch as would ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52913:3"/>all to be thought Loyal, gave the King an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of appearing more publick in that which he before durſt only diſſemble; for upon the Compliments that were daily paid him in <hi>England,</hi> he preſumed to divide the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary from the Civil Power in
<hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſetled the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation of the Standing Army in the hands of a Papiſt, who was obliged to frame it to ſuch a model as might beſt ſquare with the Turn intended: For this Service <hi>Talbot</hi> was created Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> and ſent over armed with an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Power of disbanding ſuch as he ſhould judg diſaffect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their Deſigns.</p>
            <p>At his firſt landing, he was highly courted by the Two Lords Juſtices, both of them paying him that Reſpect (tho as is ſuppos'd by the King's directions) which they ought to have received from him, and as he has been often heard to ſay, doing his Buſineſs faſter than he could have done it himſelf. Nor could the Earl of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> who ſucceeded them in the Government, ſtop <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s career; and tho he often interpoſed his Civil Authority, yet could he not prevent the whole Military Strength from devol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving into the hands of the Papiſts; for in his time were moſt of the Proteſtant Officers and Soldiers caſhier'd, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia of the Countrey diſarmed; the Forts and Strong-holds put into the Poſſeſſion of the Papiſts; and every thing elſe done, which might prepare an eaſie Acceſs ſor a Popiſh Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour.</p>
            <p>Thus far were their Deſigns advanced in <hi>Ireland,</hi> under the Umbrage of a Proteſtant Power, when <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and the great Loyalty that ſuppreſſed it, raiſed the Popiſh Party ſo far above their former hopes, that they now thought it high time to lay aſide the Mask; and to this end it was reſolved, That the Civil and Military Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhould re-unite in a Papiſt, who might act both as Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and General in that Kingdom. This double Truſt was conferred on the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> whoſe paſt Services,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52913:3"/>and avowed Prejudices to the Proteſtant Intereſt, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him as the fitteſt Perſon to Act that Part of the Tragedy; He was a man of a comely Preſence, but Haughty, Proud, and Inſolent, and therefore was not at firſt reputed Maſter of ſo much Policy and Diſcretion as he afterwards appeared to be; his open Practices againſt ſuch as Profeſſed the Reformed Religion, and his ſevere uſage of them whil'ſt he was but a Private Collonel, made them fear a ſudden Stroke from his greater Authority, upon which many of the Richeſt and moſt Powerful of the Countrey, removed themſelves with their Effects for
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and his Averſion to the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Settlement was ſo generally known, that very few durſt ſtand the Teſt of it. This great Change in the Civil Government, much Impoveriſhed and Deprived <hi>Ireland,</hi> not only of its Wealth, but of a far greater Treaſure, its Wiſeſt Men, thoſe that were left behind, being only ſuch, as altho they had known how to have helped themſelves, yet wanted both Power and Means to Effect it.</p>
            <p>Tho' the Proteſtant Intereſt was chiefly ſtruck at in this great turn, yet the Trading part of the Papiſts were alſo ſenſible of the conſequences of it; for the whole Kingdom in a ſhort time languiſhed under a general Conſumption of Trade; and the Exchequer Receipts were ſo reduced, that it was feared they would not Anſwer the publick Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. This put
<hi>Tyrconnel</hi> upon a pretended Moderation, who for ſome time concealed his Temper under a mask of gentleneſs, hoping thereby to have deluded back ſuch as had been the ſtaple Traders of this Kingdom; but they being convinced that the ſame deſigns were ſtill on foot, tho' carried on by ſlower ſteps, would not be perſuaded to re-embark their Fortunes under the Convoy of a Popiſh Pilot; <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> ſeeing himſelf thus diſappointed in his Art of Diſſimulation, reaſſumed his own Nature; and laying aſide his Hypocriſie, openly acted as the profeſſed Enemy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52913:4"/>to the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Intereſt; and having already Inveſted the Native
<hi>Iriſh</hi> with a full Power over the Lives of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, by Arming them with the Swords of Revenge, he afterwards packed ſuch Judges on the ſeveral Benches as were every way engaged to ſubvert the Legal Settlement of the whole Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the unfortunate Circumſtances the poor Diſtreſſed Proteſtants of
<hi>Ireland</hi> laboured under, when nothing but the happy News of our preſent King's Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Deſigns, could have raiſed them to the Hopes of a better Fortune; and His Majeſties good Endeavours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Crowned in <hi>England</hi> with a ſuitable Succeſs, put them upon projecting ſuch Methods as might beſt ſerve to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat their Deliverance.</p>
            <p>The only parts of <hi>Ireland</hi> where the Number of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants exceded the Papiſts, were the <hi>Northern</hi> Counties, whoſe neareſt ſeituation to <hi>England</hi> and
<hi>Scotland,</hi> had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited ſeveral Families to Tranſport themſelves thither, by which means they grew ſo Populous, that they became a Terror to their <hi>Iriſh</hi> Neighbours, and were for that reaſon believed to have been thrice as many, as they afterwards appeared to be; ſeveral Proteſtants flattered themſelves with the ſame thoughts, which proved the greateſt Spur to their preſent Confuſion; for the Gentlemen of that Countrey, preſuming too far upon the Opinion of their own Strength, and finding the Affairs of <hi>England</hi> run Succeſsfully on the Proteſtants ſide, raſhly fancied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves able enough to Attempt their Deliverance; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in daily hopes of a conſiderable ſupply from <hi>England,</hi> thought it would very much conduce to their Honour ſhould they be found in a Poſture of receiving it; but that which fixed their Reſolutions, was the neceſſity they ſeemed to lie under, of Arming themſelves againſt a Numerous Rabble, which <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> was then raiſing, and who had no other viſible means to ſubſiſt, but on the Plunder and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52913:4"/> In the Proſecution of this Affair, the <hi>L<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. B—</hi> in the Counties of <hi>Ardmagh</hi> and <hi>Monaghan,</hi> and Sir <hi>A— R—</hi> in <hi>Down</hi> and
<hi>Antrim,</hi> appeared moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; but the Councels of the latter, were chieſly manag'd by Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T—</hi> who about <hi>September</hi> 1688. ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much buſied himſelf to engage ſuch Gentlemen in an Aſſociation, as he knew his Reaſon could beſt influence; inviting them to it by urging the Probability of Succeſſes, from the current of Affairs in <hi>England,</hi> and ſhewing ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Letters from thence, which promiſed a Speedy Relief, tho in the end moſt of them proved as falſe, as the late Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts from
<hi>Londonderry.</hi> Tho this Gentleman was but of Moderate eſteem at other times amongſt them, yet his Arguments in this Conjuncture, were ſo enforced by the general Diſſatisfaction of the Countrey (ſome having juſt before loſt their Livelihoods with their Imployments, and others dayly expecting to be ejected out of their Eſtates by the corrupt Treſpaſſes on the Acts of Settlement) that they were eaſily perſuaded to joyn in any Confederacy, which might reſcue them from the approaching Ruin; and at this time their Reſolutions ſeemed confirmed, by ſuch an Opportunity as Promiſed an undoubted Succeſs to their Deſigns; for moſt of the Diſciplined Army that Quartered in the <hi>North,</hi> were juſt before embarqued for
<hi>England,</hi> in order to oppoſe our preſent King's Landing.</p>
            <p>Hitherto none of the Nobility had appeared in the Counties of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Antrim,</hi> which held ſeveral Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of thoſe Parts in Suſpence, who were unwilling to engage in an Enterpriſe of that Conſequence, unleſs Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced by Perſons of the beſt Quality, and tho other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Lords of <hi>M—</hi> and <hi>M—,</hi> were men of no extraordinary great Intereſt, yet it was generally thought more agreeable to the Rules of Policy and good Manners, that the Heads of a Party ſhould ſpring from the Nobility, whoſe precedence was Indiſputable, than
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52913:5"/>from the Gentry or Commonalty, where every man's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual pretence might breed Confuſion: It was therefore concluded, that ſuch Methods ſhould be immediately ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as might beſt ſerve to engage thoſe two Noblemen, and the E. of <hi>M—</hi> being deaf to all Arguments, was at laſt drawn in by a Letter found in <hi>Comber</hi>-Street direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his
<hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and importing the diſcovery of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Maſſacre by the Papiſts, upon the Ninth of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> following; and for the better credit of this Letter, it was pretended that notice of the ſame deſign had been ſent to <hi>H—ton</hi> of
<hi>T</hi>'s Brother, all which (as I have been very well aſſured) was only a contrivance deviſed, as the readieſt means to engage the Earl, and animate a dejected People, who of themſelves were backward to all Arguments of that Nature. However upon this Information,
<hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T—</hi> Rid Poſt for <hi>Dublin,</hi> and it was ſo ordered, that my L— <hi>M</hi>'s— Letter met him at <hi>Dundalk,</hi> by which means he went up fraighted with a double Diſcovery; The Arrival of this News at <hi>Dublin,</hi> ſo Alarm'd the City, that above Five Thouſand Proteſtants Appeared in Arms that Night, and many Hundred Families Embarqued from all Parts in ſuch Confuſion, that they left every thing but their Lives behind them; but that which hapned of greateſt conſequence upon this Diſcovery, was, the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary accident that attended the account of it in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donderry;</hi> where it had no ſooner arrived, but it ſeemed to be confirmed, paſt a doubt, by the Advance of a Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Part of the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi>'s Regiment, conſiſting of Five New-rais'd Companies, which together with the Rabble that followed, made up at leaſt a Thouſand men (deſigned for a Gariſon to the Town); the Inhabitants ſeeing ſuch a Number, and concluding them to have been the Inſtruments deſigned for the Execution of the Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Maſſacre, immediately ſhut up their Gates, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging ſome great Guns upon the nearer approach of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52913:5"/>
               <hi>Iriſh,</hi> (who were only intended for a Gariſon to the Town) obliged them to Retreat in great diſorder; and the Townſmen keeping their Gates ſhut, iſſued out a Declaration, ſhewing their Reaſons for what they had done; which they wholly imputed to the Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of a Popiſh Maſſacre; this Contrivance did very much weaken the Proteſtant Intereſt, by leſſening their Numbers; ſo did it much ſurpriſe <hi>Tyrconnel;</hi> who either ſuppoſing it to have been but a Fiction by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> had reaſon to believe it deviſed in order to promote ſome Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Deſign; or elſe, knowing it to have been really inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, could not but be touched with the Diſcovery of it: The Effect was, it haſtned the Advance of Forces in all parts of the Kingdom; <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> having diſpatch'd Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Letters to the ſeveral Counties, encouraging the raiſing of men, by promiſing to each Perſon a Commiſſion ſuitable to the Number he ſhould Liſt; The Earl of <hi>Meath, Grenard,</hi> and other Proteſtant Peers, Reſiding at that time in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and foreſeeing the Evil Influence that would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow the Conjunction of ſo vaſt a Rabble joyned in a Remonſtrance, and Petitioned, That no more Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might iſſue; but received ſuch an Anſwer, as haſtned the Earl of <hi>Meath</hi> for <hi>England,</hi> under colour of Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Melancholly Circumſtances of that Kingdom; but what Service he did for the Countrey (tho it be many Months ſince) we are not yet ſenſible of.</p>
            <p>The raiſing of theſe New Levies, was the great ſtep to thoſe heavy Misfortunes that ſoon afterwards fell upon the whole Kingdom; for their Officers having abandon'd them to their own ſhifts, and the Government allowing no other ſubſiſtence than what they could Plunder from the Proteſtants, brought ſuch a Fate upon the Gentlemen of <hi>Lemſter</hi> and
<hi>Munſter,</hi> that moſt of them enjoyed but one days ſpace between Riches and Beggary. Amidſt theſe Convulſions, the <hi>North</hi> only remained undiſturbed; for
<hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connel</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52913:6"/>not having yet raiſed any conſierable Numbers, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Feared than Deſpiſed them; and the News of what hapned in <hi>Londonderry,</hi> made him dread the Conſequence of ſuch an Example; which put him upon engaging my Lord <hi>Mountjoy,</hi> to uſe his utmoſt Intereſt and Endeavours towards the Reduction of that Town; who after ſome Debate, and upon Condition, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſhould be firſt Disbanded, was admitted with Five Companies; and being under an obligation of returning, Recommended the Care of the Gariſon to his Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Lundy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Matters being thus far Accommodated in <hi>Derry,</hi> and <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> being willing to ſecure himſelf againſt the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern</hi> Numbers, Prudently reſolved to keep up a fair Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with them; and in order to it, he invited ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the Leading men to attend him at <hi>Dublin;</hi> but the Countrey not judging it ſafe to venture many of them, leſt they ſhould be detained as Hoſtages; nor Politique, wholly to deſpiſe his Summons, concluded that only Sir <hi>Robert Colvil</hi> ſhould be entruſted with this Undertaking; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very kindly treated by the Government, was diſmiſſed with repeated Aſſurances, That if his Countrymen would continue quiet in their Reſpective Habitations, they ſhould be only charged with the Incumbrance of Two Regiments; but as it ſoon afterwards appeared, <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> had never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to keep theſe Promiſes any longer than they ſerved his Deſigns; for immediately upon Sir <hi>Robert</hi>'s departure, he Commanded a Detachment out of another Regiment to reinforce the Gariſon at the <hi>Newry.</hi> It's likewiſe to be preſum'd, that Sir
<hi>Robert Colvil</hi> promiſed more in behalf of the <hi>Northern</hi> Gentlemen, than they were willing to make good; for at his return he found them engaged in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which as well in reſpect of his Promiſe, as in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prudence, he thought himſelf obliged to oppoſe; judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it not fit to incenſe a Government that courted them, eſpecially ſuch a one as he very well knew they could not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52913:6"/>be able to oppoſe, ſhould they be reduc'd to extremity, being ſenſible that the <hi>Northern</hi> Strength conſiſted much more in Reputation, than in any real Force they could make; but all his Endeavours were vain, and his Advice branded with the Epithetes of
<hi>Cowardly</hi> and <hi>Popiſh,</hi> by thoſe who had afterwards Reaſon to wiſh they had yielded to ſuch Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Councils.</p>
            <p>The Two Regiments which by <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s engagement were deſigned for the
<hi>Northern</hi> Quarters, hapned at this time to be Gariſon'd in <hi>Lysburn, Bellfaſt, Carrickſergus,</hi> and other adjacent Places, under the Command of the Earl of <hi>Antrim,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Newford;</hi> when upon a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn debate by a Committee of ſuch as had ſubſcried the Aſſociation, it was concluded that thoſe Regiments ſhould be diſarmed, and the Caſtle of <hi>Carrickfergus</hi> ſecured, in which were Arms for Two Regiments more. Upon the Strength of this Attempt they purpoſed to have oppoſed <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> upon equal Terms, and by putting a Gariſon into the <hi>Newry,</hi> they hoped to have ſtop'd that Paſs, and thereby to have ſecured the two Counties of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Antrim</hi> for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Intereſt. This project ſeemed the more Feaſible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one Hundred and Fifty of <hi>Newcomen's</hi> Regiment, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting only of 500. were Proteſtants, and ready to joyn in the execution of this Deſign, offering as a farther demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their good will to the Publick Service, an excellent Stratagem for the Surpriſe of the Caſtle at
<hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> which they propoſed to effect, under the pretence of their Collonel's purpoſe to Gariſon there; but the failure of their Deſigns againſt <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> rendered this Contrivance uſeleſs, which hapned in this manner. When the Project of Diſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Popiſh Soldiers in that Town was upon Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Sir <hi>W— F—,</hi> Mr. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>—,</hi> and Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T—,</hi> together with Capt. <hi>Leighten,</hi> Capt. <hi>Berning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Lieut. <hi>Barnes,</hi> Lieut.
<hi>Tubman,</hi> and ſeveral other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Regiment, and Citizens of the Town, met in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52913:7"/>order to accompliſh their Deſigns; but the firſt three, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting, abſolutely deni'd to go on, tho often preſſed to it by the Officers; Capt. <hi>Leighton</hi> urging the Feaſibleneſs of it, by engaging to Diſarm the whole Gariſon, with the aſſiſtance only of as many men as might ſerve to bring off their Arms; but the three firſt Gentlemen diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing the Captains offer, and interpoſing their great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with the Town, the whole Project fell, and <hi>H———ton</hi> of <hi>T—</hi> Gallopped towards Sir <hi>Arthur R—,</hi> who Marching with Five Hundred men to make good the Attempt, was advanced within Five Miles of the Town; when this ungrateful Meſſage diverted him, and occaſioned his giving ſuch marks of Reproach, as was due to thoſe who had ſtifled ſo hopeful a Deſign: Thoſe who had been appointed to Seize the Popiſh Arms in <hi>Lisburn,</hi> having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the advantage of the night, did the work; but their Correſpondence at
<hi>Belfaſt</hi> aſſuring them of a failure by the Undertakers of that Town, made them dread the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of being ſolely expoſed to the Revenge of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; which conſideration put them upon returning thoſe Arms they had taken; the ſeveral Gentlemen who Commanded in the Army, having by this vain Attempt Diſcovered their averſion to the Popiſh Intereſt, Marched off with 150 of their men, hoping thereby to prevent any Surpriſe, which might have afterwards betrayed them into the hands of their Collonel, who likewiſe finding his Number very much decreaſed by the Deſertion of ſo many of his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and fearing the conſequence of a Second Project, Retreated in all haſte to ſafer Quarters: The Gariſon of the <hi>Newry</hi> (which at that time only conſiſted of two Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies) hearing of the Proteſtant Deſign againſt the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in <hi>Lisburn</hi> and <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> and expecting a ſudden onſet from the Inhabitants of that Town, quitted their Poſts, and could not be perſuaded to return, till they were firſt aſſured of the Unhappy failure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:52913:7"/> As this miſcarriage proved a Warning-piece to alarm the Popiſh Party; ſo on the other hand it very much diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Proteſtant Intereſt; for ſeveral Gentlemen (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as were to have been actually engaged in this Attempt) being apprehenſive of the dangers that might attend ſuch timorous Councils, provided for their future ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by ſecuring a Paſſage for <hi>England;</hi> and <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> being now convinced of the
<hi>Northern</hi> Deſigns againſt his Government, immediately reinforced the Gariſon at the
<hi>Newry,</hi> thereby ſecuring an eaſie entrance into the <hi>North,</hi> and intercepting all Correſpondence between the <hi>Northern</hi> and other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; which proved a matter of ſuch Conſequence, as by this means no Letters or Meſſengers were ſuffer'd to paſs or re-paſs, but ſuch as he knew would beſt ſerve his turn.</p>
            <p>The Gentlemen who had been the unhappy occaſion of all theſe Miſchiefs, being ſenſible of the unfortunate Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances to which they had reduced that Countrey, now began to conſider of ſuch methods as might make amends for their paſt Miſcarriages: To this end a General Meeting at <hi>Comber</hi> was concluded on, in which they might agree what Courſe next to ſteer, and how for the future to lay ſuch a Scene of Affairs, as might give them a better Proſpect of Succeſs. Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> appearing moſt officious upon this occaſion, and having undertook the Diſpatch of Circular Letters, ſummon'd only ſuch as he knew would be either guided by his Counſels, or elſe wanted Intereſt to oppoſe his Deſigns; for he neither ſummon'd Mr. <hi>Anneſly,</hi> Sir <hi>Rob. Maxwell,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ward,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Savage,</hi> nor any other Gentleman whom he believed would not readily reſign a blind aſſent to his humour, tho they were otherwiſe Perſons every way qualified for the Publick Service: But that which hapned of greateſt difficulty, was the excluſion of Sir <hi>Rob. Colvil</hi> from this Meeting, whoſe great Eſtate in the Countrey, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the very Town where they ſate, ſeemed to oblige them to take notice of him; but it was ſo contrived, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52913:8"/>the Gentlemen who were deſigned for Council, aſſembled on the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, at which time the methods were concluded on, and Sir <hi>Rob.</hi> ſummoned the next day, to aſſent, if he pleaſed, to what he could not alter. This Convention, which only conſiſted of Sixteen Gentlemen, being ſat at <hi>Comber,</hi> the firſt things diſcourſed of, were the Diſorders, Delays, Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and other Inconveniences that attended their former Meeting, to which the failure of their Deſigns was chiefly attributed; and to obviate thoſe Miſchiefs, it was agreed, That a <hi>Junto</hi> of Five ſhould be choſen for the County; any Three whereof ſhould be empowered to act as the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives of the reſt, whoſe Decrees and Orders ſhould be as binding, as if they had been concluded by the general Voice of the Countrey.</p>
            <p>And it was likewiſe agreed, That an Aſſociation ſhould be propoſed by the Gentlemen of that County, to the other Counties of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> for the joint Preſervation of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Intereſt, and Protection of the Proteſtant Religion. Matters being thus far adjuſted by the conſent of the whole Convention; the next thing to be conſidered, was the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Five ſuch Perſons as were beſt qualified to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the County; and for that ſervice, the E. of <hi>M—</hi> Sir <hi>A—R—,</hi> Mr. <hi>H—</hi> of
<hi>B—,</hi> Mr. <hi>H—,</hi> and <hi>H—</hi> of <hi>T—,</hi> were propoſed at the inſtance, and by the directions of the latter; who having packed the greateſt part of the Aſſembly, could not want a Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Votes to declare in favour of ſuch as he thought fit to recommend.</p>
            <p>Theſe Gentlemen being complimented with a tender of the Care and Truſt of the County, at firſt as modeſtly refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as the New Pope does the Papacy, which they after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards as willingly embraced; and tho ſome of the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thought others far better qualified, both in Intereſt, and Parts, for a Charge of that Conſequence, particularly Sir <hi>Rob. Colvill,</hi> whom they would have at leaſt compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52913:8"/>with the choice of being one, conſidering his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune was almoſt equal to the Joint-Eſtates of the other Five, and that his Age and Experience had rendred him much fitter for an Employment of that nature; but <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T—</hi> being well aſſured that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> would not be prevailed with to ſerve any private Deſigns, paſſionately oppoſed all Motions in his favour; and for want of a better Argument, threatned to deſert the Aſſembly, if they ſhould admit a Propoſal ſo averſe to his Intereſt. Till this Meeting at <hi>Comber,</hi> many thought <hi>H—ton</hi>'s earneſt Sollicitations had proceeded from a real Concern for the Proteſtant Intereſt; but it was now plainly diſcovered, that the whole ſcope of his Deſigns tended only to ſettle him in ſuch a Poſt as might render him more remarkable to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government.</p>
            <p>The Convention having inveſted the <hi>Junto</hi> with the whole Power of the County, were of courſe diſſolved, and the <hi>Junto</hi> immediately withdrew from the reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, in order to act ſeparately, in purſuance of their new Commiſſion: It was firſt determined, That a fit Perſon ſhould be ſent with an Addreſs to our preſent King, congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulating His Happy Acceſs to the Throne, and imploring the Aſſiſtance of
<hi>England</hi> for their ſpeedy Relief; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Gentlemen were propos'd for this Expedition; but none ſo generally approved of as Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> of <hi>Comber,</hi> who beſides his other Qualifications, had a juſt pretence to the Employment, having been formerly choſen for this Service by the Vote of the whole County; but <hi>H—ton</hi> of
<hi>T—</hi> fearing perhaps that he might by this oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity foreſtall his Deſigns, ſet up Capt. <hi>Leighton</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to his Kinſman, and by his Intereſt ſo far prevailed, that the Captain was preferred to this Honourable Errand; Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> ſeeing himſelf thus poſtponed by the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of his own Relation, and the Honour conferred on his Competitor without the leaſt Apology for rejecting him, was ſo highly ſenſible of the Abuſe, that he ſoon after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards quitted the Countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:52913:9"/> Whilſt theſe things were debated in Council, ſeveral Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes arrived from <hi>Dublin,</hi> which by Publick Orders were immediately carried to the
<hi>Junto,</hi> and ſome Gentlemen then in Town, who had been always privy to the former Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpendence, being denied a ſight of theſe laſt Accounts, very much reflected upon the meaſures newly taken, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting but ſlender returns from a Council, who in its very Infancy preſumed to act ſo arrogantly, diſobligingly, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and imprudently: The <hi>Junto</hi> fearing the conſequence of theſe Publick Cenſures, very much laboured to quiet the minds of the Male-contents, who began to unravel the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Methods by which they were convened, and to proteſt againſt the evil Arts that eſtabliſhed them. The next day, according to the return of his Summons, Sir <hi>Rob. Colvill</hi> came to Town, on whoſe Appearance it was judged conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to admit him of the Council, hoping thereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile themſelves to the Gentlemen of the Countrey; and to make way for him, my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Mount-Alexander</hi> was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed General of the Forces of the two Counties of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Antrim:</hi> Sir <hi>Robert</hi> being admitted, the <hi>Junto</hi> proceeded to nominate Five Perſons out of every Barony to repreſent the Condition of it, propoſing by this method a clearer view of the Strength and Force of each County; and it was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moved and agreed, that every County for its better intelligence ſhould ſubſtitute one Perſon to be always reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent at <hi>Hilsburg,</hi> by which means the ſeveral Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the <hi>North</hi> might be the better underſtood, and the execution of their Deſigns be for the future grounded on more united Reſolves. To this purpoſe it was judged neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that a general Aſſociation ſhould be ſubſcribed by the Gentlemen of that Province, and that the Methods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by this <hi>Junto,</hi> ſhould be propoſed as an Example to the neighbouring Counties; Sir <hi>W— F—,</hi> who with Mr.
<hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T.</hi> had formerly contrived the Aſſociation, went to my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
               <hi>Maſſareen</hi>'s, where he had appointed the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52913:9"/>Gentlemen of the County of <hi>Antrim</hi> to meet, who on the next day appeared to the Number of Five and Thirty, and Sir <hi>William</hi> having addreſſed himſelf to them, propoſed the ſeveral Decrees of the County of <hi>Down,</hi> as a Preſident fit for them to follow; urging the Conveniency of a ſeparate Council, as alſo ſeveral Arguments to induce them to a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſociation; but my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Maſſareen,</hi> and ſeveral of the Gentlemen, earneſtly oppoſed it, alledging the want of Arms and Experience, both which were judged to be ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedently neceſſary to ſo publick a Declaration, which would otherwiſe rather prove a means to haſten their ruin, than to promote their Deliverance; and for that reaſon they inclin'd to wave the thoughts of an Aſſociation, and only join in a private Addreſs; but Sir <hi>W— F—</hi> preſſing it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them by many ſpecious Arguments, urging, That it would convince the King of their Readineſs to ſerve his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; and that the People of <hi>England</hi> would be thereby obliged to ſend them a more early Supply, prevailed with the greateſt part of them to Aſſociate, and appoint a certain Number of Gentlemen for their Repreſentatives; tho they would not agree to the ſame Methods with the County of <hi>Down,</hi> who inveſted their <hi>Junto</hi> with an Abſolute Power, not approved of by any other County. <hi>Antrim</hi> having thus far agreed to what had been propoſed, in the next place proceeded to an Election, and made choice of Sir <hi>William Franklyn,</hi> Mr.
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Davis,</hi> Mr. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Shaw,</hi> for their
<hi>Junto;</hi> and the County of <hi>Ardmagh</hi> following the ſame courſe, elected Sir
<hi>Nich. Atcheſon,</hi> Capt. <hi>Points,</hi> and <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leton;</hi> but <hi>Derry, Donnegal,</hi> and <hi>Tyrone,</hi> abſolutely refuſed to reſolve themſelves into any Committee; neither could they be perſwaded to agree to an Aſſociation, and yet they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe put themſelves in a Poſture of Defence, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Col. <hi>Lundy;</hi> but the other Project of a Reſident at <hi>Hilsburgh,</hi> was ſo generally approved, that each County, in purſuance of the Methods propoſed by the <hi>Junto</hi> of <hi>Down,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:52913:10"/>recommended their ſeveral Repreſentatives, who when they met, formed themſelves into a General Aſſembly, and in a little time aſſumed the power of a Supreme Council: The ſeveral Gentlemen who were preferred by their reſpective Counties to this great Truſt, were as follows, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pton</hi> for <hi>Antrim,</hi> Capt.
<hi>Poynts</hi> for <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cunningham</hi> for <hi>Derry,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Johnſten</hi> for <hi>Monaghan,</hi> and Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T—</hi> for
<hi>Down,</hi> who were Convened under the Preſidency of the E. of <hi>Mount-Alexander.</hi> The Conſtitution of this Aſſembly did in a great meaſure ſupercede all Inferior Juriſdictions; eſpecially in that County where they ſat; ſo that the <hi>Junto</hi> of Five became by this means of little or no uſe, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the whole Management of
<hi>Down</hi> fell under the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T—,</hi> who at their firſt Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion propoſed to diſpatch Capt. <hi>Leighton</hi> with an Addreſs to the King; but that matter having received its firſt Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the former <hi>Junto,</hi> the reſt of the Council thought fit that nothing ſhould be determined without their approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Conſent; and it was therefore ordered that Letters ſhould be ſent to ſummon the
<hi>Junto;</hi> and by ſome private Inſtructions Sir <hi>Rob. Colvil</hi> was induſtriouſly omitted, who believing it to proceed from the former Prejudices, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the buſineſs of the Addreſs already agreed on, to be the only occaſion of that Meeting, did not give himſelf the trouble of appearing that Seſſion; but when he afterwards found that Capt.
<hi>Leighton</hi> was not only engaged to Preſent the Addreſs, but likewiſe entruſted with a particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation of ſuch Perſons as were judged fitteſt for the Military Service, he then concluded they had omitted him with a deſign of forecloſing his Pretences to that Poſt in the Army, to which his Eſtate and Intereſt in the Countrey would have entitled him; but that which encreaſed his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments, was to find the ſeveral Precincts of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try allotted to each Col. for the raiſing of his men; and that his Eſtate was appointed to that Perſon whom he had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52913:10"/>the greateſt reaſon to ſuſpect for the only Author of this Abuſe. No ſooner was a Journal of the Proceedings of this Seſſions Publiſhed, but the Countrey generally exclaimed againſt the Injuſtice done to Sir <hi>Rob. Colvil;</hi> and to amuſe the People, it was ſome time afterwards propoſed to meet at Sir <hi>Robert</hi>'s Houſe, under colour of acquainting him with ſuch Papers and Inſtructions as they had ſent by Capt.
<hi>Leigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton;</hi> being well aſſured, that the Injury done him, was now paſt retrieve, Capt. <hi>Leighton</hi> having received his Credenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and being at that time ready to embark for <hi>England.</hi> Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> upon peruſal of the Addreſs, ſeemed better ſatisfied with the ſlight they had placed on him, becauſe ſeveral Particulars of it did not only contradict his private Senſe, but were alſo contrary to the general Opinion of the whole Countrey; for firſt, It was ſuppos'd they flatter'd themſelves in giving too great a Character of their own ſtrength; and that propoſing only twelve Regiments to be newly raiſed for the Defence of the <hi>North,</hi> ſeemed as if they either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not the Power of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> or elſe had a mind to betray their Countrey. In the next place they greatly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their own weakneſs, by joining Five Counties in the raiſing of Twelve Regiments, which <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> always believed able to have advanced above Fifty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men; and tho it was propoſed that each Regiment ſhould conſiſt of 13 Companies, and every Company of 100 men, yet this was likewiſe judged imprudent, becauſe many Gentlemen were thereby excluded, who would have readily commanded a Company, tho unwilling to ſerve as a
<hi>ſubaltern</hi> in ſuch a Militia. They were alſo very much condemned for appointing the ſeveral Officers for each Company, without conſulting them whether they were willing to ſerve; but that which fixed the greateſt Reproach upon them, was the particular Returns of ſeveral Collonels; for knowing their own County would not afford them ſcope enough to provide for all their Confederates, they preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52913:11"/>to reverſe the Decrees of other Counties, without the Privity of their Repreſentatives; this practice is very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, in the Affront they placed upon Capt.
<hi>Poynts,</hi> whoſe former good Services in the Army, and Intereſt in <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> had recommended him to the Character of being Reſident for that County, and was afterwards repreſented as a Perſon beſt qualified to command their Forces; but <hi>H—ton</hi> of
<hi>T.</hi> fearing it might be inconſiſtent with his Deſigns to admit this Gentleman to a place ſo conſiderable, pretended ſome urgent Affairs to be tranſacted in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of
<hi>Ardmagh,</hi> in which Capt. <hi>Poynts</hi> was engaged; and the other taking the advantage of his Abſence, procured that Command for a Gentleman of his own name; the Capt. being returned as Lieut. Col. to Sir <hi>John Macgill,</hi> and finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thus abuſed, ſeparated from their Council, and for ever after denied to act in Conſult with thoſe who had ſo baſely betrayed him.</p>
            <p>The Twelve Regiments recommended for Commiſſions, conſiſted of 8 Foot, 2 Horſe, and 2 Dragoons, which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their Collonels and Counties, take as follows, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>E. of <hi>Mount-Alexander,</hi> a Regiment of Horſe to be raiſed in <hi>Down</hi> and
<hi>Antrim.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>Blany,</hi> a Regiment of Horſe in <hi>Ardmagh, Monaghan,</hi> and
<hi>Fermanagh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Skeffington,</hi> Dragoons in <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Antrim.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Arthur Rawdon,</hi> Dragoons in <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Antrim.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Macgill</hi> Foot, <hi>Down.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> of <hi>Bangor,</hi> Foot, <hi>Down.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T.</hi> Foot, <hi>Down.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Francis Hamilton,</hi> Foot, <hi>Ardmagh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Will. Franklyn,</hi> Foot, <hi>Antrim.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pton,</hi> Foot, <hi>Antrim.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Leſley,</hi> Foot, <hi>Antrim.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Montgomery,</hi> Foot, <hi>Fermanagh.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:52913:11"/> Beſides theſe Twelve Regiments intended to have been raiſed by Commiſſion; there were ſeveral Gentlemen of greater Intereſt in their reſpective Counties, tho not thought ſo fit to be returned by the <hi>Junto;</hi> who purely upon their own Credit, advanced a great Number of men; for in the County of <hi>Down,</hi> Sir <hi>Rob. Colvil</hi> raiſed a full Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and Mr. <hi>Adare</hi> another in the County of
<hi>Antrim;</hi> and many more Independent Troops and Companies were Levied by ſeveral Gentlemen, who propoſed no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for their Service, but the Publick good; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would not value their Intereſt at ſo cheap a rate, as to become private Centinels to ſuch as were very much their Inferiours, in Birth, Experience, and Eſtate. The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, who had been thus forward to reſtore their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, amongſt whom Mr. <hi>Anneſly;</hi> who by being bred a Soldier abroad, was both able and willing to ſerve, having at his own expence, raiſed a full Troop of Dragoons, and two Hundred Foot in the <hi>Barony</hi> of <hi>Kinelcarty,</hi> had their Services when offered, Rejected by the Governour.</p>
            <p>The raiſing of Independent Troops and Companies, turned very much to the diſadvantage of ſeveral Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who had friends enough in the Council to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them for Commiſſions; but wanted intereſt in the Countrey to raiſe their men; but this fell heavieſt upon Mr.
<hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T</hi>'s—Regiment, who having that Precinct aſſigned him, where the Countrey had been pre-engaged to a better Intereſt, could never advance above 300. men; whereas the Volunteer Regiments conſiſted of three times that Number.</p>
            <p>No ſooner were theſe things acted in the <hi>North,</hi> but <hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connel</hi> received an exact Account of them in <hi>Dublin;</hi> and believing my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Mountjoy</hi> to have been the private ſpring that ſet the Countrey in this motion; diſpatched an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to him, by which he was kindly entreated to return; but his Lordſhip being at that time very much indiſpoſed,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52913:12"/>offered his want of Health, as a reaſon to excuſe his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance. This Anſwer confirmed <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer jealouſie, and made him more ſollicitous to diſengage my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Mountjoy:</hi> who was at laſt prevailed with to quit his Countrey; and being come to <hi>Dublin,</hi> was flattered with <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s Treacherous Deſigns of ſurrendring the Kingdom; having often heard him ſay, that he could eaſier make it a heap of rubbiſh, than any way ſerviceable to the Late King <hi>James.</hi> My L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Mountjoy</hi> being deluded by thoſe. Arts and Contrivances, into a belief of what was never really deſigned; was the eaſier perſuaded to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a Voyage for <hi>France,</hi> under pretence of acquainting the Late K. with the Circumſtances of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connel</hi>'s Opinion in relation to the Surrender of it. And for the greater amuſement of his Lordſhip, and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the <hi>North,</hi> ſeveral Articles were Condeſcended to, which were very much in Favour of the Proteſtant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; for before my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Mountjoy</hi> was prevailed upon to engage in this expedition, <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> had ſolenly Promiſed to put a ſtop to the intended Levies, and to disband ſuch as were but lately raiſed; he likewiſe declared againſt Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering any more Soldiers upon the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter;</hi> or making a Gariſon of any private Houſe; and my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy</hi> in the Name of the Proteſtants, tho without any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from them, engaged for their good Behaviour, ſo long as thoſe Promiſes ſhould be kept, and until a return ſhould be made to this pretended Errand. The differences in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſeemed at this time very far advanced towards an accommodation; and it's generally believed all acts of hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity would have continued under a ſuſpence, if my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy</hi> had been the only perſon entruſted with this Meſſage; but when the Proteſtants found that <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> had recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended one Sir <hi>Stephen Rice,</hi> who was then Chief Baron, and a moſt Inveterate Papiſt, to be his Lordſhip's Colleague In this Expedition, they began to ſuſpect the Deſigns of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52913:12"/>
               <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and it was generally believed that my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Mountjoy</hi>'s Commiſſion, only ſerved as a facing to the Chief Baron's private Inſtructions. It cannot be imagined that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip could be wholly ignorant of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s double Deſign in this Conjuncture; tho perhaps being once in <hi>Dublin,</hi> he could not have eaſily avoided his Commands; but his Lordſhip fearing the cenſures he might incur, from his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie compliance with them; ſet himſelf to write an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for engaging in this Embaſſy, in which he juſtified his Undertaking, tho againſt the Opinion of the <hi>Northern</hi> Proteſtants, from the private aſſurances he had of <hi>Tyrcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi>'s Reſolution; which he could better judge of, than his Friends at a greater diſtance; and beſides this Letter to the <hi>North,</hi> his Lordſhip writ other Letters to ſome Perſons of Quality in
<hi>Munſter,</hi> urging them to keep that Countrey in a peaceable expectation of his Lordſhip's return; and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to it, by engaging (in an expreſſion of his own)
<hi>that all would end in a Can of mild Beer:</hi> Notwithſtanding theſe Endeavours uſed by my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Mountjoy</hi> to reconcile the Countrey to a good Opinion of this Undertaking, every ordinary Capacity could judge, That this Errand was chiefly pretended, to give <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> the better Opportunity of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on his Deſigns; and it was generally believed, that my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
               <hi>Mountjoy</hi> was only made uſe of to prevent his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of engaging on the Proteſtant Party; which was afterwards confirmed by <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s abuſe of all his Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and his Lordſhip's Impriſonment in <hi>France.</hi> The loſs of a Gentleman ſo conſiderably qualified for the Publick ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, gave a mighty blow to the Proteſtant Intereſt; but more eſpecially to the affairs of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> in that it made way for the Supream Council to chuſe the E—of <hi>M</hi>—for their General; who being wholly ignorant of all Military Diſcipline, and not much prepared for ſo great a Command, reſigned himſelf ſometimes to the directions of Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T.</hi> a Perſon leſs qualified than his Lordſhip,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52913:13"/>being of Moderate Reputation for his Conduct, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo unhappily fond of his own Opinion, tho never ſo inconvenient, that no arguments could alter him.</p>
            <p>This Gentleman was entirely Governour both of the General and the Council, ſo that whatever he propoſed, paſſed beyond all contradiction for a Rule to the reſt.</p>
            <p>The Countrey began to be jealous of the great Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Gentleman; having formerly ſuſpected his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity from his favourable carriage towards the Papiſts at the Quarter-Seſſions; which together with his many Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Relations, and great intimacy with Col. <hi>Marcus Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot,</hi> baſe Son to <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> made many fear that the Game began to be a little more tickliſh than formerly on the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ſide: And that which daily encreaſed their jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, was the ſeveral unfortunate events that alter'd his Councils; for having (as is ſaid) aſſumed to himſelf an abſolute Power over the Governours and Council, ſo as all things moved by his directions, it ſo hapned that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing proſper'd in which he had a hand, very little being attempted in his time, which did not ſavour either of folly or ignorance; and tho ſeveral good Propoſals had been made, yet they were either not taken notice of, or elſe open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejected; as for inſtance, It was moved that a Pacquet-Boat ſhould be ſetled between the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> and tho nothing was urged againſt, yet it was never effected. The want of Arms and Ammuition was complained of, and ſeveral ways Propoſed for the purchaſe of them; but they were judged needleſs, for <hi>England</hi> would ſupply all; when ſecuring and fortifying ſome places for a Retreat in caſe of Extremity, was diſcourſed of, that was judged unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, for we ſhould be able to deal with them in the Field; and at laſt when the Enemy came down and expected to have been oppoſed, the Paſſes were all opened, and inſtead of Uniting the Proteſtant Forces, they were induſtriouſly Diſperſed, and by that means expoſed to the loſs of their Countrey without having one ſtroke for it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52913:13"/> But to proceed from what they left undone, to what they did, the firſt thing Reſolved on, was a neceſſary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of Money, the Sinews of War, and ſeveral methods were Propoſed for the raiſing of it; as Firſt, by calling a private Seſſions, in which they might charge the Country, under a pretence of finiſhing the Bridge begun at
<hi>Belſaſt;</hi> but this was condemned as inconvenient: Then it was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that Money ſhould be advanced upon the publick Faith; but that was feared to have been almoſt Bankrupt. It was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Propoſed, That the Revenue might be Confiſcated; but his was not agreed to, till the Collections were all drawn off; ſo that the only Methods conluded on, was, by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Contributions, either in Money, or Goods, as might beſt ſuit with the Gentlemen's convenience; and it was Ordered for the better Collection and Diſpoſal of them, that Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> of <hi>Bangor</hi> ſhould be Receiver, and Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T</hi>'s— Diſpoſer. The Gentlemen of the Countrey, and Merchants of <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> having ſubſcribed to ſuch Sums as they were able or willing to advance; Copies of their Subſcriptions were diſperſed into the ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and propoſed as an example to induce others to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute; amongſt the reſt <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T</hi>—for his part ſubſcribed Thirty Pounds, which he pretended to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct from One Hundred Pounds due to him, for ſo many Barrels of Beef, at 20 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> per</hi> Barrel, laid in by him for the Publick uſe; but Beef being then at 12 <hi>
                  <abbr>s.</abbr> per</hi> Barrel, this piece of Policy was ſo obvious, that inſtead of being a good Example, it hindred many Gentlemen from Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing; who ſeeing in the diſpoſers own Gifts a certain Profit, concluded that the ſame uſe would be made of theirs; and when it was afterwards deſired that an account ſhould be given of the Receipts and Disburſements, it was only An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; <hi>That Superiors ought not to account to their Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors:</hi> But however ſeveral places were Garriſon'd; and the Soldiers maintained, tho it is ſaid, their beſt Subſiſtence was upon the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Plunder. open acts of Hoſtility being
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52913:14"/>now common to both Parties; inſomuch as the Frontier Towns were quite waſted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> in this juncture buſied himſelf in a cloſe Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with the
<hi>North,</hi> encouraging them to follow their Husbandry; and aſſuring them that he would Surrender the Government, upon the return of my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Mountjoy;</hi> but theſe expreſſions were only made uſe of as a Cover to his Deſigns; for at the very ſame time he was raiſing New Levies, and as it was confidently Reported, gave out Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions for above 40000 Men. Amongſt other <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, who by theſe New Commiſſions were advanced to be Collonels, <hi>Cormuck O Neale</hi> of the County of <hi>Antrim,</hi> who at that time had Profeſſed himſelf a Church Papiſt, was engaged by the Government to raiſe a Regiment on the Confines of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Antrim;</hi> but the Proteſtant Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of that County, ſuppoſing him to have been drawn in contrary to his inclinations, adviſed him againſt the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of it, which he ſeemingly ſubmitted to; but as ſoon as his Lieut. Col. <hi>Felix O Neale</hi> came into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, they privately raiſed their Regiment on both ſides the
<hi>Ban;</hi> and immediately Marched that part of them which Quartered on this ſide of the River, to Gariſon <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rickfergus;</hi> but ſuch as lay on the other ſide, could not be ſo eaſily brought over, for fear of the Proteſtants in <hi>Antrim;</hi> and <hi>Cormuck O Neal</hi> being very ſollicitous to ſecure a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for the reſt of his men, purpoſed to have done it by making himſelf Maſter of <hi>Tuam</hi> Paſs; but being well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the Proteſtants would be jealous of any of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Troops, he was therefore forced to pretend a fear of being diſarm'd by Col. <hi>Stuart's</hi> Soldiers; under Colour whereof he hoped to ſecure the March of a Troop of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons to <hi>Tuam;</hi> but this Project was too groſs to impoſe on the Proteſtant Party, who immediately Purſued the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons with a ſmall Detachment; and having given them a Total Defeat, and Diſperſed that Part of <hi>O Neale</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, They built a ſmall Fort at the Paſs, and Gariſon'd it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52913:14"/>with 60. men, thereby intercepting all correſpondence with the Papiſts beyond the <hi>Ban.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Succeſs of the Proteſtants in the confines of the County of <hi>Antrim,</hi> and of the L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Blany</hi> in ſome ſmall Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes in <hi>Armagh</hi> and <hi>Monaghan,</hi> raiſed the Ambition of the County of <hi>Down,</hi> who had not hitherto approved their Courage to Attempt ſomewhat that might make them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable; and having often in their Cups Threatned the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gariſon in the <hi>Newry,</hi> which had always lain forgot, aſſoon as they grew Sober, now either found or made a Noble occaſion of trying their Strength and Policy againſt <hi>Carrickfergus;</hi> which by the acceſſion of <hi>Cormuck O Neale's</hi> New-rais'd men, conſiſted of Nineteen Companies, beſides the Countrey that daily flockt to that Town, as being the only Popiſh <hi>Aſylum</hi> in thoſe Parts. The Proteſtants begun to grow jealous of the great Numbers crowded into that Gariſon, and to prevent the miſchiefs that might ſpring from ſo great a Concourſe of <hi>Iriſh,</hi> they ordered ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions as were deſigned for that place, to be intercepted; and amongſt others, Col.
<hi>Edmunſton</hi> by command from the Council, ſeized on a Boat Laden with Proviſion, at
<hi>Broad-Iſland;</hi> which was intended for my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Antrim</hi>'s private Family, and ſent it croſs the <hi>Bay</hi> to <hi>Bangor,</hi> whither the Enemy could not advance but through
<hi>Belfaſt.</hi> The Earl incenſed at this uſage, threatned to Burn the Collonel's Houſe; who to prevent any attempt of that Nature, had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it with a Gariſon of 100. Men; and the ſame deſign be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing declared againſt <hi>Bangor,</hi> Col. <hi>Hamilton</hi> made the ſame Proviſion againſt it. The Council upon ſecond thoughts, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Boat and Proviſions to be reſtored; but Col. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> under whoſe Command it then lay, judged it not convenient to obey their Orders, having with the advice of Sir <hi>William Franklyn</hi> and ſome others of the Council, reſolved to Attack the Town. The E. of <hi>Antrim</hi> and his Officers, having propoſed a Parley which was agreed to by the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and his Council, met at
<hi>Belfaſt</hi> where the <hi>Iriſh</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:52913:15"/>remonſtrating the unreaſonableneſs of intercepting their Proviſion; and finding the great concourſe of People to be the only reaſon offered by the Proteſtants, in excuſe of their uſage, they deſired leave to divide their Numbers, and that ſome of their Soldiers might Gariſon in <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> or any other indifferent place; but this propoſal was reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unleſs the Earl would firſt ſuffer them to be diſarm'd; which he obſtinately refuſed, but offered to disband the New Levies, if they could be inſured of a peaceable Living in their reſpective Houſes: The Gentlemen, who preferred the Quiet of the Countrey, thought this to have been a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient condeſcention, and that the Proteſtants might have thereby gain'd a very great point, at leaſt in Reputation; but it made a diſterent impreſſion on the General and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, who believing this eaſie Compliance to have proceeded from an inward diſtruſt of their own Strength, concluded that nothing was wanting but a bold Attempt to make themſelves Maſters of that Gariſon. This Deſign was chiefly promoted by
<hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T</hi>—, hoping thereby to make amends for his paſt Miſcarriage; and countenanced by the General, who never failed of a ready Aſſent to ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, as the other thought fit to propoſe: Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi> of <hi>Bangor</hi> was particularly concern'd to forward the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; fearing leſt the Neighbourhood of that Gariſon, might prove dangerous to his private concerns, being ſenſible of the provocations he had given them, by detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Earl's Boat and Proviſion. Sir <hi>W—F—</hi> was likewiſe engaged in promoting the Attempt; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rendred himſelf particularly obnoxious to
<hi>Tyrconnel</hi> by his Correſpondence with him; he reſolved to reſcue himſelf from the apprehenſions of falling into his hands, by leaving the Kingdom; but being at that time entruſted with the Command of a Regiment, and his Soldiers having Notice of his Deſigns, forced him againſt his Inclinations to Stand to his Arms; which made him willing to undertake any Attempt, how deſperate ſoever, hoping thereby to wipe off the Aſperſion of his paſt Endeavours.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:52913:15"/> Theſe were the ſecret Springs upon which this Project turned, againſt the general Opinion of the reſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; and theſe Gentlemen, with ſome of the disbanded Officers, were the chief Promoters of this Enterpriſe, which was oppos'd by Sir
<hi>Rob. Celvill,</hi> Mr. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pton,</hi> and moſt of the Countrey; who eaſily foreſaw the difficulties that attended it, and would have diſſwaded them from engaging in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign that would infallibly end in a diſcovery of their own weakneſs, and in all probability would haſten down <hi>Tyrcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi>'s Forces againſt them, which they were in no condition to oppoſe; but all theſe Objections were anſwer'd by the ſtrong Reaſon which was always ready upon ſuch occaſions, <hi>viz. That they knew beſt what was fitteſt to be done; and that to queſtion their Reſolutions after the Truſt rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed in them, tended only to Diſorder and Confuſion.</hi> Having reſolved to attack <hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> the following Stratagem was agreed on, as the beſt Expedient to effect it: Mr. <hi>Davis,</hi> an Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant of that Town, whoſe Hoſpitality and good Humour had rendred him very much eſteemed by the Popiſh Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, was engaged to give them ſuch a hearty Welcome, as might drown all ſenſe of their Duty, and make them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of oppoſing the Proteſtant Onſet; the Deſign being thus laid in the Town, Circular Letters were diſpatched from <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> to ſummon the Countrey Regiments to Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous by Five the next morning, near <hi>Carrickfergus;</hi> who notwithſtanding the ſhort Warning, great Diſtance, and Winter Seaſon, were very punctual to the Commands of their General, and appeared at the Time and Place, to the Number of 3000; and tho they had undergone the Fatigues of a Rainy nights March, in a very deep way, yet were they ſo forward to approve their Courage, that nothing but the poſitive Commands of their Officers could prevent their fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the Enemy, whoſe chief Commanders were ſo well ſecured by <hi>Davis</hi>'s Eiquor, that it's generally believed our Soldiers might have taken the Town, by killing only the Out Centinels; but here our General and his Council, tho
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52913:16"/>to blame before, for their ſudden Reſolutions, thought fit to act with greater deliberation; and inſtead of executing their former Reſolves, they now began to conſult anew, by which means they gave the Officers time enough to ſleep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſober, and the Gariſon an opportunity of calling a Council of War, who believing the Town not to be in ſuch a Poſture of Defence as would oppoſe the ſudden aſſault of an Enemy provided with all things neceſſary for a general Attack, judged it convenient to beat a Parley; which was readily accepted by our General; and Col. <hi>Talbot</hi> being ſent from the Town to manage the Conference, entertain'd our General with ſuch Trifles, as it plainly appeared that nothing was deſigned by the Enemy, but the diſcovery of our Strength, and the gaining ſo much time as might prepare them for a defence; for having mann'd their Walls, and lin'd ſome Hedges without the Town, they took no farther notice of the Parley, but Sallied on the Suburbs, Killing Plundering, and Firing all that lay before them: Upon this treacherous Abuſe, and the diſcharge of their Cannon, it was propoſed that Col. <hi>Talbot</hi> ſhould be ſecured for a breach of the Truce; but our General judging it neither Honourable nor convenient, diſmiſs'd him with a ſafe Convoy to the Town; and having afterwards advis'd with his Council, they unanimouſly agreed upon a general Attack, tho they had neither Cannon to Batter, nor Ladders to Scale, nor any other Proviſion fit for ſuch an Attempt. It is not yet known what Paſſion moved them to this deſperate Reſolution; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is ſaid by ſome, that it was chiefly undertaken out of a fear they had, that the E. of <hi>Antrim</hi> would lay down his Arms to ſave his Eſtate; which was ſo conſiderable, that they had rather give him this fair opportunity of offending, than not oblige him to a forfeiture; for certainly they could not be ſo ſtupid (tho we have no great reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their Prudence) as to flatter themſelves with the hopes of taking a Wall'd Town, well Mann'd and Fortified, with the only Artillery of Pikes and Muskets.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:52913:16"/> Whatever the Motives were, that induc'd them to a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſeemingly ſo unreaſonable, their Reſolves were confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Army divided into ſeveral Battalions for a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſault, who upon the firſt Word of Command, in defiance of the Enemies Cannon, marched up to the very Walls of the Town; which they would have undoubtedly taken, if Pikes and Scythes could have prevailed; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpent their Ammunition, and experienced the impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of the Attempt, they were at laſt obliged to retreat, which they perform'd with no great loſs; but their Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation was rather due to Providence, and the indiſcretion of their Enemies, than to the Care or Conduct of their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, or Council; who after they had given Orders for the Attack, left their Soldies expoſed to the Cannon, and reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red under the Shelter of a Barley Field and Pidgeon-houſe, hoping thereby te ſecure themſelves from the Noiſe and Danger of the Enemies Shot. The news of this Retreat having advanced as far as the Head-Quarters; the General and his Council concluded upon a Parley; and being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved it ſhould end in Peace, the Soldiers were commanded to their former Quarters; in this conjuncture it was thought the Town might have propoſed their own Terms, but Col. <hi>Talbot</hi> being willing to return the Civilities lately received, only inſiſted upon the ſame Propoſals that had been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made by the Earl of <hi>Antrim,</hi> and deſir'd that a Ceſſation might be punctually obſerved on both ſides, 'till ſuch time as freſh Supplies ſhould be ſent from <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The General and Council facing their ill Succeſs with the pretended Advantages they boaſted to have gain'd upon this Parley, returned as it were in Triumph to <hi>Hilsburgh;</hi> but it cannot be ſuppoſed that they were wound up to ſuch a degree of inſenſibility, as not to be touch'd with a ſenſe of their misfortunes, conſidering they had failed in an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which was undertaken upon their bare humour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Directions and Advice of the reſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; the evil Conſequence that followed the Proteſtant's
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52913:17"/>Defeat at <hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> ſo far encouraged the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that they immediately ventured upon Publick Acts of Hoſtility, plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Proteſtant Houſes at <hi>Noon day,</hi> and Maſſacring ſuch as they thought would have oppoſed their Villanies: And now the Dragoons of the <hi>Newry,</hi> who never before durſt quit their Gariſon, ventured themſelves abroad, and having intelligence of the advance of a Proteſtant Party under the Command of Capt. <hi>Poe,</hi> which had been detatch'd from
<hi>Loughbrickland</hi> for Forage, they laid an Ambuſcade, and by a Surprize killed the Captain and Eight of his men.</p>
            <p>As theſe and many other unfortunate Accidents which enſued the Defeat at
<hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> very much advanced the Reputation of the Popiſh Party; ſo on the other ſide, it made a quite different Impreſſion on the Proteſtant Soldiers, who were ſo far diſcouraged by their ill Succeſs, and for ever after entertained ſo mean an opinion of their General and Council, that for the ſuture they never yielded an exact Obedience to their Commands.</p>
            <p>Upon this Defeat at <hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> there arrived a Packet of Declarations at
<hi>Hilsburgh,</hi> directed to the General, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Requiring all the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to lay down their Arms by the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> on pain of being accounted Rebels, with an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Pardon and Protection to ſuch as embrac'd the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals, and a promiſe of the Eſtates of the obſtinate, to ſuch perſons as ſhould contribute towards their Reduction. This Declaration was ſo careſſed by the Ptoteſtants, that they cauſed them to be publickly read in ſeveral Market Towns, and at the ſame time proclaimed K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary.</hi> This great Solemnity was ſcarce over, when Capt. <hi>Leighton</hi> returned with Commiſſions for ſuch Regiments as had been recommended by the Council; but there being at this time ſome Regiments and ſeveral Independent Troops and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies which were not eſtabliſhed by any of theſe new Commiſſions, and were to be of courſe thereby disbanded, it was very much to be feared that this great Change might widen the Breaches already begun between the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52913:17"/>Countrey and their Council; for the better preventing of which, it was propos'd, That the Countrey ſhould act in their own Model, till ſuch time as more Commiſſions were ſent over; and that in the interim, all Perſons ſhould join their ſtrength to avert the dangers that Threatned their Speedy Rume; but this met with the Fate of ſeveral other good propoſals, and was generally rejected.</p>
            <p>Now Danger began to draw near; of which <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s Proclamation was a Forerunner; Commanding all Perſons in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> to give up their Arms, and Serviceable Horſes, with an offer of Pardon to all ſuch as had been any way Engaged, excepting the E. of
<hi>Mountalexander,</hi> L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reen,</hi> L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Kingston,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Sheffings,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Colvill,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Rawden,</hi> Sir <hi>John Macgill,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hawkin's,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hamilton,</hi> now Sir
<hi>Francis Hamilton,</hi> who were ſaid to have Sinned beyond his Mercy; ſeveral of thoſe Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were ſent into the <hi>North,</hi> and induſtriouſly diſtributed to the Gentlemen of that Countrey, who remained fixed to their former Reſolution, notwithſtanding the many Threats and Promiſes that were urged to perſuade them to other Meaſures. Theſe coming to the hands of <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T.</hi>—, he burned them, inſtead of diſperſing them.</p>
            <p>Such Gentlemen as read this Proclamation, were not a little ſurpriſed to find ſeveral Perſons, who had always ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared moſt Active and Open in the Proſecution of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Deſigns, not comprehended in the clauſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption; for neither Mr. <hi>H — ton</hi> of <hi>T</hi>—, who was the moſt Active, and indeed the Principal manager of the whole Affair, who had a caſting Voice in all their Councils; nor any of the
<hi>Hamiltons</hi> of <hi>Down, Antrim,</hi> or <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, tho Gentlemen that Acted in Conjunction with them; and others that were Inferior to them, were parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly exempted; but this only ſerved to revive the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer jealouſie the Countrey had of Mr.
<hi>H.</hi> of <hi>T</hi>'s ſincerity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> who at this time was undoubtedly privy to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular circumſtance that hapned in the <hi>North,</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52913:18"/>perhaps had been the chief Contriver of what was Tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Now he began to think it convenient to prepare his Army for a March towards thoſe Parts; and having made a neceſſary Proviſion for the ſubſiſtance of his Soldiers, he diſpatched part of it to
<hi>Carrickfergus</hi> by Sea, which was then in want, and the reſt he ſent by Land; but it hapning that one of his Ships Laden with Bisket, was forced into <hi>Dundium Bay,</hi> and immediately Seiſed by the Proteſtant Gariſon, and ſent to the publick Stores, to be laid up for their March againſt the <hi>Iriſh.</hi> From theſe Preparations it was generally concluded, that <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s Army would be ſuddenly on it's March, and therefore thought adviſeable that ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Meaſures ſhould be taken, as might beſt ſerve to oppoſe their entrance; but ſo it hapned, that in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture, a News Letter was pretended to have been receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Council; and tho all Correſpondence between <hi>Dublin</hi> and the
<hi>North</hi> had been intercepted for a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time before, yet this Letter came dated from thence, and was induſtriouſly Diſperſed by ſome of the Council, as a true account of the Popiſh Circumſtances; in which were contained ſeveral Arguments to urge the Improbabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Marching an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army <hi>Northward,</hi> chiefly drawn from the intractable Genius of the New-rais'd Forces, their want of Arms and Ammunition, and the general Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion they lay under from the Proteſtant Numbers, and the Landing of an
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Army. Theſe obſervations, with ſeveral other leſs remarkable, were the ſubject-matter of this Letter; which coming down at a time, when the whole Countrey was big with the expectation of an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, the News whereof had been confirm'd by ſeveral particular Accounts, made different impreſſions upon the Proteſtant Gentlemen; ſome of them ſuppoſing it to have been deviſed by <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> and ſent down on purpoſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſe the Countrey; hoping thereby to render his Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons leſs ſuſpected; but this conſtruction being inconſiſtent with his Printed Proclamation, was generally rejected; and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52913:18"/>tho it ſeemed very hard to place this contrivance upon any of the Council, which only tended to the confuſion of their former Deſigns; yet there were ſome amongſt them, who were ſeverely cenſured for their too great Induſtry in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing it, when it was in their Power to have it ſuppreſſed.</p>
            <p>This Letter, tho it weighed but little with the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Countrey; yet the General and Council ſeemed ſo far convinced by the reaſons of it, that they Poſtponed their former reſolve of Providing againſt the approach of the Enemy; for tho they had always propoſed to fortiſie and ſecure <hi>Hilsburgh</hi> for a Retreat, it being the only Fort in <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Antrim,</hi> excepting <hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> which lay convenient for the Defence of the Frontiers, and was at that time a Magazine of all their Arms and Ammunition; yet they rejected all offers that were made in purſuance of their former Deſigns; and neither ſuffered the Trenches to be Scoured, nor Commanded any other thing to be done which was neceſſary for the Defence of it; tho the Inferior Councils being more ſenſible of their Duty, Fortified and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red many places of leſs conſequence. <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s Forces being advanced under the Command of Lieut. Gen. <hi>Hamilton,</hi> within an eaſie days March of the <hi>North,</hi> the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ſeeming more apprehenſive of the dangers that might attend their former ſecurity, buſied themſelves in a warmer application to their General and Council, who being now ſenſible of their credulous Error, promiſed to uſe their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Endeavours againſt the approach of the Enemy; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they made a ſhow of drawing the Forces of the two Counties into one Body, which being above 10000 men, would in all probability been able to have diſputed, if not defended the Countrey from the farther advance of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army; tho it muſt be confeſſed, the greateſt part of them wanted the Exerciſe and Arms of a well Trained Militia; but that might have been in a great meaſure ſupplied by the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Propoſals of ſome Gentlemen, who advis'd that the Paſſes might be Guarded by their beſt men, and ſuch only left to ſecure their Countrey, as were leſs Serviceable.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:52913:19"/> If theſe Meaſures had been taken, we ſhould have certainly impeded the Enemies Progreſs, and have thereby given time enough to the more <hi>Northern</hi> Counties, to have joined their Numbers, who had been engag'd to advance upon the firſt Alarm; but the General and Council, inſtead of following this advice, only continued their Forces in motion, ſtill keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them at their former diſtance; which Method was the great occaſion of our enſuing Miſeries; for the ſeveral petty Diviſions deſparing of any Succeſs from their own Strength, never durſt encounter the Enemy, who always Marched in a main Body. The firſt inſtance of this Nature hapned at <hi>Loughbrickland,</hi> a place within 3 Miles of the
<hi>Newry;</hi> where only a Detachment of Sir <hi>John Macgil</hi>'s Regiment, and an inconſiderable party of Sir <hi>Arthur Rawden</hi>'s Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, were poſted, who no ſooner heard that <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had enter'd the <hi>Newry,</hi> but they retired in ſuch confuſion, that the whole Countrey ſeemed ſtruck with the Retreat. The Enemy making the right uſe of this accident, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately poſſeſſed themſelves of <hi>Loughbrickland,</hi> and ſoon after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards advanced towards <hi>Drummore,</hi> which was Gariſon'd by 300 Horſe, and ſome Foot, under the Command of Sir <hi>Arthur Rawden,</hi> and Mr. <hi>W</hi>—, who having notice of their March, poſted a Detachment of Horſe at the 2 Mile Bridge, with ſtrict Orders to Skirmiſh the Enemies Scouts, and to give what other diverſion they could to their Main Body; but having engaged too far, ſeveral of them were cut off, and the reſt obliged to a haſty Retreat. Sir <hi>Arther Rawden</hi> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tinued in the Town,' very minute, expecting to be inforc'd with a conſiderable Supply, but was much ſurprized to receive the General's Orders to Retreat to <hi>Hilsburgh,</hi> which was three Miles behind <hi>Drummore.</hi> This ſudden diſappointment made him reſolve upon his own Methods; and inſtead of Retreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Hilsburgh,</hi> he marched his men within view of the Enemy, whom he diſcovered to be very numerous, and advancing in great haſte, but excellent Order; which made Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> halt, and conſulting with his Officers what was
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52913:19"/>fit to be done, he found his Right Wing ſurrounded; and concluding the Enemy deſigned to hem in his Party, they all agreed upon a Retreat; and the only doubt that remained was, who ſhould be formoſt. Lieut. <hi>Price,</hi> and two others, after the Retreat of the reſt, bravely charged the Enemy, and <hi>Price</hi> having ſhot Col. <hi>Sheldon</hi>'s Horſe, by which he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much endangered his Life, was afterwards, by the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure of his own, expoſed to the Revenge of the <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bold Attempt of theſe three men, gave a conſiderable diverſion to the whole Army; ſo that in purſuit of the Proteſtant Party, which haſted full Gallop to <hi>Hilsburgh;</hi> there were not above 20 men kill'd; but if the Fort had not put a ſtop to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Career, they had certainly cut off the reſt, who under that ſhelter made good their eſcape, ſome to <hi>Colrain,</hi> others to <hi>Portferry,</hi> every one ſteering ſuch a Courſe as he judged fartheſt from the preſent Danger.</p>
            <p>The General and Council had hitherto reſided in <hi>Hilſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> which was the place appointed for the heart of the <hi>North,</hi> from whence the ſeveral Counties were to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived their Principles of Motion; and yet they were ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of defending a Poſt ſo conſiderable, that the day before this Rout, it had not the ordinary Proviſion of a Gariſon; for on that day Mr. <hi>Weſt,</hi> (Major to Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T</hi>— was commanded to advance with ſuch of his men as were fit for ſervice, who in purſuance of their Orders, enforced the Town with 120 men, and propoſing the Defence of it with the only addition of
500 more, at leaſt till ſuch time as the ſcattered Forces of the <hi>North</hi> might be drawn together, who might have been able to have raiſed the Siege,) had his offer reſiſted, tho there were at this time in <hi>Lisburn</hi> 2000 Soldiers ſent from the County of
<hi>Antrim;</hi> and the only reaſon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the General and Council for rejecting
<hi>Weſt</hi>'s Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, was the want of neceſſary Proviſions for ſo great a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: The Major not being well ſatisfied with the Meaſures taken by the Council, was however reſolved to uſe his beſt Endeavours towards ſecuring the Town, and only deſired
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52913:20"/>to be furniſh'd with ſuch Inſtruments as might ſerve to ſcour the Trenches; and that the Trees which grew neareſt the Town, might be cut down, leſt they might prove ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Enemy, in caſe they ſhould attempt to Scale the Walls; but theſe requeſts were alſo rejected, the firſt for want of Money to buy ſuch Neceſſaries as were deſired, and the other for fear of diſobliging the Owners; theſe ſlight Excuſes made the Gentlemen of the Countrey ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſome other Deſigns; which were ſoon afterward plainly diſcovered by the Reſolutions taken in the next Council: The General having declared the Town not te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, turned every man over to his own ſhifts. The Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were ſo much ſurprized with this ſudden opinion, that they would not be induc'd to a belief of it 'till their General left the Gariſon expoſed to the rage of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and in great haſte poſted towards <hi>Portferry,</hi> where he met with the conveniency of being tranſported out of all danger. Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T</hi>— having particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended the care of his Regiment to their own Conduct, haſted towards <hi>Belfaſt</hi> in ſuch a hurry, that he left behind him a Portmantue of the publick Papers, and 150 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> of the Counties Stock, tho he refuſed the day before to advance ſo much Money as would have brought the Forces together. This, with much more Plunder of a conſiderable value, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides 15 Barrels of Powder, and a braſs Field-piece, were left as a prey to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who have ſince made uſe of the Papers as a publick Teſtimony againſt the perſons concerned in the Aſſociation, upon which has been grounded the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Blood, and forfeiture of our Eſtates.</p>
            <p>Tho <hi>H—ton</hi> of <hi>T</hi>— had been thus careleſs of what concern'd the Publick, yet he ſhew'd more prudence in the preſervation of his private Fortune: For, very well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what would happen, he engag'd his Brother the night before the Break at <hi>Drummore,</hi> to haſten home, and provide againſt the Storm that was then gathering.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hilsburgh</hi> being wholly deſerted by the General and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52913:20"/>Council, Major <hi>West,</hi> who had earneſtly preſſed them to other meaſures, was ſtill reſolv'd to ſell the Place at as dear a price as he could; and therefore propoſed the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of it to ſuch of the Soldiers as yet remain'd in the Fort, aſſuring them of his firm adherence to their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and urging the many difficulties that would neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily attend their retreat. But all theſe Arguments could not engage them to ſtand the teſt of an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Attack; for the Example of their General, and the Advice of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, ſo far influenc'd their wonted Courage, that only Sixty of them could be prevail'd with to run the Major's Fate; who diſpos'd of them in ſuch order, as made the
<hi>Iriſh</hi> believe they were many times that number; upon which they ſent a Trumpeter to ſummon the Town; and a Parley be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing agreed on both ſides, Capt. <hi>Kirk</hi> was diſpatched with Conditions of Surrender, importing a free Pardon for what was paſt, and a Protection for the future; which being embrac'd by the Gariſon, and confirm'd by the Lieutenant-General, the
<hi>Iriſh</hi> were admitted into the Town; and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Gates only ſhut with a Half-Pike, admired the Majors courage, and condemned the General and Council for making no better preparations towards the defence of a place ſo conſiderable. Major <hi>Weſt</hi> and his Soldiers not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their Articles, were for the firſt night kept cloſe priſoners, under the pretence of protecting them from the inſolence of the Soldiers; tho the true reaſon was to prevent a diſcovery of the ill circumſtances the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army was under, from the fatigue of their tedious Winter March, which was ſo haraſs'd, that it's believed a very little oppoſition would have obliged them to a retreat.</p>
            <p>The melancholly news of this Rout coming to <hi>Lisburn,</hi> and the diſmal accounts given in by the Runaways from <hi>Hilsburgh,</hi> ſtruck the Soldiers of that Gariſon, with ſuch terrible apprehenſions of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Force, that they unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly agreed to follow the example of their General, and Mr. <hi>H</hi>—. of <hi>T.</hi> after he had for ſome time condol'd the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52913:21"/>misfortunes of the Countrey with the People of <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> he aſſured all ſuch as had any dependance on him, that would retreat to <hi>Colrain,</hi> that he had reſolved either to repair the diſtreſſed Condition of the Countrey, or to permit the the Attempt. This Reſolution encouraged ſeveral of his Friends to march towards
<hi>Colrain,</hi> but Mr. <hi>H—ton</hi> taking a private Path to the Sea-ſide, met with a Veſſel purpoſely prepared to Tranſport him for <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rabble of the whole Countrey were now em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by Publick Authority to plunder and deſtroy the Lives and Fortunes of the Proteſtants; which they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with ſuch Cruelty, that the Inſolencies of the Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army ſeemed favours, when compared with the bloody Outrages of thoſe barbarous Cannibals; and now the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Cries of ſuch as had eſcaped the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Fury for the loſs of their deareſt Friends, and the naked Appearances of thoſe who had been moſt inhumanly ſtripped, caſt the whole Countrey under ſuch a general Conſternation, that it was impoſſible to revive the hearts of the dejected Proteſtants; ſo that no hopes were left to rally the broken pieces of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army; and the Enemy by this means became abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Maſters of the whole Countrey, without the expence of many drops of Blood; for the Counties of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trim</hi> being the only Inlets to the <hi>Northern</hi> Province, we may very well date the loſs of
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> (at that time the only remaining terror to the <hi>Iriſh</hi>) from the evil Succeſs that followed the Councels of that Countrey.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now refer the remaining Series of this Affair, to the relation of others, who by being Witneſſes to the Truth thereof, are only fit for ſo publick a Work; having in this Treatiſe with all Sincerity and Juſtice imaginable, given the Reader the whole matter of Fact, which to my own knowledg occurr'd in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Counties. And that he may have nothing from me by hear-ſay, I ſhall now leave him to judg by whom and in what manner <hi>Ulſter</hi> has been expoſed to the Fury of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> whoſe Mercies are Cruelties: And how all the Nobility and Gentry thereof have ſuffered as well in their Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as in the loſs of their Eſtates, for the Miſcarriages of a few.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
